Guide to the Andrew Sarris Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Andrew Sarris Papers,
1948-1988
[Bulk dates: 1965-1985]
Sarris, Andrew.
20.42 linear ft.
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1451
6892031
The Andrew Sarris Papers are comprised of correspondence, drafts and manuscripts, clippings, printed ephemera, periodicals, monographs, photographs, and audio recordings related to the career and personal life of renowned film critic Andrew Sarris. The materials span several decades, from the inception of his career as a film critic and theorist in the mid-1950s to the last years of his long tenure at The Village Voice in the late 1980s..
Biographical Note
Andrew Sarris was a prominent American film critic, perhaps known best for giving credence to the European auteur theory in the United States. Born October 31, 1928 to Greek immigrant parents, he was raised in Ozone Park, Queens. Sarris graduated from Columbia University in 1951, and subsequently served in the United States Army Signal Corps from 1952 to 1954. Though his zeal for film developed at an early age, Sarris’ career in film criticism formally began in 1955 when he met Jonas Mekas, co-editor of the fledgling journal Film Culture, who enlisted Sarris to contribute to the publication.
Sarris wrote for Film Culture for several years. In 1960, Mekas, at that time a film reviewer for The Village Voice, asked Sarris to substitute for him. Sarris’ first article, a controversial piece on Alfred Hitchcock’s Psycho, appeared in the Voice on August 11, 1960. The article became the first of many, and Sarris continued to write for the Voice for nearly thirty years. It was also around this time that Sarris developed a deep interest in French cinema; in particular, he was drawn to the New Wave movement and the critical approaches to film that were concomitant with its emergence.
Inspired by French critic François Truffaut and other contributors to the journal Cahiers du Cinema, he wrote "Notes on the Auteur Theory in 1962," which appeared in Film Culture. In this contentious essay, Sarris espoused the concept that a film directly reflects the director’s creative vision; essentially, film is a director’s artistic medium, and should be critically analyzed and appreciated as such. His essay aroused considerable dissension from other critics, and sparked the notorious dispute between himself and Pauline Kael.
Though controversial, Sarris managed to propagate the auteur theory, and it became a fixture in the dialect of American film criticism. In his 1968 book The American Cinema: Directors and Directions, 1929-1968, Sarris expanded on the auteurist approach, and the work became a seminal opus in the canon of film literature. He later contributed a number of other influential books, such as Confessions of a Cultist(1970), The Primal Screen(1972), and Politics and Cinema(1978).
In addition to journalism, Sarris held a professorship at Columbia for many years. He also taught courses at Yale, NYU, The School of the Visual Arts, and Juilliard. He received a number of awards and accolades including the Rockefeller Fellowship at Bellagio (1991), a Guggenheim Fellowship (1969), Officier de l’Ordre des Arts et des Lettres (1982), the Special Award from the L.A. Critics Circle (1985), the Maurice Bessy Award, Montreal (1995), and was a runner-up for the Pulitzer Prize for Criticism (2000).
Sarris married feminist film critic Molly Haskell in 1969. The two met when Haskell worked at the French Film Office in New York. They remained married until his death on June 20, 2012.
Scope and Content
The Andrew Sarris papers are comprised of personal and professional correspondence, drafts of various pieces published throughout his career, manuscripts of screenplays, clippings of pieces written by and about Sarris, press releases, printed ephemera, filmic periodicals and monographs, film stills, and recordings of Sarris’ "Films in Focus" radio program.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in seven series.
Series I: Correspondence, 1952-1988, undated
Series II: Drafts and manuscripts, 1961-1986, undated
Subseries I.1: Drafts, undated
Subseries I.2: Manuscripts, 1961-1986, undated
Series III: Printed material, 1952-1988, undated
Subseries III.1: Clippings, 1960-1988, undated
Sub-subseries III.1.1: Articles by Sarris
Sub-subseries III.1.2: Articles mentioning Sarris
Sub-Subseries III.1.3: General articles
Subseries III.2: Press releases, 1952-1988, undated
Subseries III.3: Printed ephemera, 1963-1988, undated
Subseries III.4: Monographs, 1960s-1980s
Subseries III.5: Periodicals, 1960s-1980s
Series IV: Photographs, undated
Series V: Recordings, 1965-1969, undated
Series VI: Family papers, 1953-1970, undated
Series VII: Personal files, 1945-1980, undated
Subjects
Haskell, Molly.; Sarris, Andrew.; Columbia University.; Cahiers du cinema.; Film culture.; Village voice (Greenwich Village, New York, N.Y.); Auteur theory (Motion pictures).; Film criticism.; New wave films.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Drafts (documents); Film stills; Magnetic tapes; Manuscripts (document genre); Monographs; Notes; Periodicals; Press releases; Printed ephemera; Screenplays
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Selected Related Material-- at Columbia
Reminiscences of Andrew Sarris: oral history, 1981.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1952-1988, undated
  This series is comprised of both personal and professional correspondence. Arranged chronologically, the series contains mostly incoming and some outgoing correspondence. This includes, but is not limited to, correspondence between readers, students, publishers, and university officials. There are also a number of letters from notable directors, including Martin Scorsese, Clint Eastwood, Orson Welles, and Oliver Stone, as well as actors such as Christopher Walken and Shirley MacLaine.
  - 1952-1974 (Box 1)
  - 1974-1980 (Box 2)
  - 1981-1988 (Box 3)
  - Undated (Box 4, Folder 1-5)
- Series II: Drafts and manuscripts, 1961-1986, undated
  This series is comprised of drafts and rough notes, in various stages of completion, which Sarris generated over the course of his career. It also contains manuscripts of screenplays written by Sarris, in addition to a number of manuscripts written by others and likely submitted to Sarris for feedback.
  - Subseries 1: Drafts, undated
    As a majority of the drafts are fragments and virtually none are dated, this subseries is not arranged in any particular order, but is separated between complete and partial drafts. “Complete drafts” are defined as pieces that are essentially whole and whose titles can be identified, whereas partial drafts are more fragmented and thus difficult to classify by title.
    - Complete (Box 4, Folder 6-10)
    - Partial (Box 4, Folder 11-17)
    - Partial (Box 5, Folder 1-8)
  - Subseries 2: Manuscripts, 1961-1986, undated
    The bulk of the material in this subseries is authored by others; however, there are three screenplay manuscripts written or co-written by Sarris: Promise at Dawn (1964), Justine (1964), and the undated Wickford Point. Manuscripts by others includes both screenplay and book manuscripts. Of note are two undated screenplays by King Vidor that were never produced as films. The manuscripts authored by others are separated between screenplays and books, and are arranged alphabetically by author.
    - Manuscripts by Sarris
      - Justine, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Promise at Dawn, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Wickford Point, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Manuscripts by others
      - Screenplays
        - Buchman, S., Promise at Dawn, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 12)
        - Delynn, J., The Imprisoned Queen of England, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 13)
        - Dozier, R., The Cardinal, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 14)
        - Edwards, B., S.O.B., 1979 (Box 5, Folder 15)
        - Gibson, W., Two for the Seesaw, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 16)
        - Hill, J., Identical Twins, The, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
        - Mayes, W., Advise and Consent, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 18)
        - Moffat, I., Tender is the Night, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 1)
        - Moss, L., Lily, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 2)
        - Sarafian, R.C., Andy, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 3)
        - Snell, M., White Meat, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 4)
        - Vidor, K., The Actor, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
        - Vidor, K., Bright Answer, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Books
        - Biskind, P.Seeing is Believing, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 7-10)
        - Levy. E., John Wayne: Prophet of the American Way of Life, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 11-13)
        - Maghsoudlou, Iranian Cinema (Volume I), undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
        - Maghsoudlou, Iranian Cinema (Volume II), undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
        - Maghsoudlou, Iranian Cinema (Volume III), undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
        - McCreadie, M. Women on Film: The Critical Eye, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 1)
        - Raphael P., Beating the Love Affair Rap and Other Stories, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        - Sikov, E.K. Hollywood Screen Comedy in the 1950s, undated (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
        - Surguy, P. Mister Cinema: A Critical Biography of Rex Skinner, undated (Box 7, Folder 5-7)
        - Untitled manuscript, undated (Box 7, Folder 8-10)
      - General (Box 7, Folder 11-12)
- Series III: Printed material, 1952-1988 undated
  This series is diverse and is thus arranged in five subseries. It is comprised of both published material and printed ephemera.
  - Subseries 1: Clippings, 1960-1988 undated
    This subseries is comprised of clippings of articles authored by Sarris, articles mentioning Sarris, and general filmic articles collected by Sarris throughout his career.
    - Sub-subseries 1: Articles by Sarris
      This sub-subseries mostly contains clippings of Sarris’s Village Voice articles, which are arranged chronologically. This sub-subseries also features clippings of articles Sarris wrote for other publications.
      - Village Voice, 1960-1988 (Box 7, Folder 13-19)
      - General publications, 1962-1986 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Sub-subseries 2: Articles mentioning Sarris
      This sub-subseries contains articles that mention Sarris. Book reviews are separated from general articles.
      - Book reviews, 1967-1984 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - General, 1969-1987 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Sub-subseries 3: General articles
      This sub-subseries contains clippings of film-related articles collected by Sarris throughout his career.
      - General articles, 1961-1987 (Box 8, Folder 3-16)
  - Subseries 2: Press releases, 1952-1988, undated
    This sub-series contains press releases Sarris collected throughout his journalistic career. These include releases from agencies such as Universal Studios and the American Film Institute. Though some are undated, they are arranged chronologically where possible.
    - Press releases, 1952-1988, undated (Box 8, Folder 17-18)
  - Subseries 3: Printed ephemera, 1963-1988, undated
    This sub-series contains a broad array of material, and includes programs, flyers, pamphlets, posters, and invitations. The ephemera in this series relate mostly to special events, film festivals and screenings Sarris attended throughout his career.
    - Printed ephemera, 1963-1988, undated (Box 8, Folder 19-20)
    - Printed ephemera, 1963-1988, undated (Box 9, Folder 1-6)
  - Subseries 4: Monographs, 1960s-1980s
    This sub-series contains film-related monographs.
    - Monographs, 1960s-1980s (Box 9)
  - Subseries 5: Periodicals, 1960s-1980s
    This sub-series contains filmic journals and magazines. Most are American publications, but there are also a number of French titles. Titles with a significant number of issues include Cahiers du Cinema, Films in Review, Films and Filming, and Sight and Sound. They are arranged alphabetically by title, and each title and its corresponding box number is listed in the finding aid.
    - Action! (Box 10)
    - American Federation of Film Societies Newsletter (Box 10)
    - American Film (Box 10)
    - American International News Clips (Box 10)
    - Art Films (Box 10)
    - Bianco e Nero (Box 10)
    - Black Film Review (Box 10)
    - Castle of Frankenstein (Box 10)
    - Cahiers du Cinéma (Box 10)
    - Cahiers du Cinéma (Box 11)
    - Cahiers du Cinéma in English (Box 11)
    - Canadian Cinematography (Box 11)
    - Cineaste (Box 11)
    - Cinefile (Box 11)
    - Cinema (Box 11)
    - Cinema # (56-62) (Box 11)
    - Cinema Canada (Box 11)
    - Cinéma Français (Box 11)
    - Cinema Today (Box 11)
    - Cinématographe (Box 11)
    - Cinémonde (Box 11)
    - Columbia University Film Review (Box 11)
    - Copie Zero (Box 11)
    - Études Cinématographiques (Box 11)
    - Film (Box 11)
    - Film 9 (Box 11)
    - Film Comment (Box 11)
    - Film Culture (Box 12)
    - Film Directions (Box 12)
    - Film History (Box 12)
    - Film Journal (Box 12)
    - Film News (Box 12)
    - Film Notes (Bulletin of the MoMA) (Box 12)
    - Film Society Review (Box 12)
    - Film Survey 1 (Box 12)
    - Films and Filming (Box 12)
    - Films and Filming (Box 13)
    - Films in Review (Box 13)
    - Film in Sweden (Box 13)
    - Film Quarterly (Box 13)
    - France in the United States Monthly (Box 13)
    - Hollywood Reporter, The (Box 13)
    - Home Video (Box 13)
    - Image et Son (Box 13)
    - Imagery (Box 13)
    - Independent, The (Box 13)
    - International Film Review (Box 13)
    - Journal of the Producers Guild of America, The (Box 13)
    - Journal of Popular Film, The (Box 13)
    - Journal of Popular Film and Television (Box 13)
    - L’Avant Scène (Box 13)
    - L’Écran (Box 13)
    - La Biennale de Venezia (Box 13)
    - La Femme à l’Écran (Box 13)
    - Laser Disc Newsletter, The (Box 13)
    - Les Grandes Créateurs Du Cinéma (Box 13)
    - Letter From France (French Film Office) (Box 13)
    - Mid-Century, The (Box 13)
    - Millimeter (Box 13)
    - Miroir du Cinéma (Box 13)
    - Motion (Box 13)
    - Movie (Box 13)
    - Movie Story (Box 14)
    - Moviegoer (Box 14)
    - National Board of Review Magazine (Box 14)
    - New Canadian Film (Box 14)
    - New Zealand Film (Box 14)
    - NY Film Bulletin (Box 14)
    - Objectif (Box 14)
    - Otro Cine (Box 14)
    - Perspectives: Flashes sur l’Histoire du Cinéma (Box 14)
    - Plays and Players (Box 14)
    - Premiere (Box 14)
    - Présence du Cinéma Français (Box 14)
    - Premier Plan: Hommes Oeuvres Problemes du Cinema (Box 14)
    - Positif (Box 14)
    - Saturday Review (Box 14)
    - Scenario (Box 14)
    - Screen Romances (Box 14)
    - Screen Facts (Box 14)
    - Sequence Four (Box 14)
    - Skoop (Box 14)
    - Seventh Art, The (Box 14)
    - Showbill (Box 14)
    - Sight and Sound (Box 14)
    - Stop (Box 14)
    - Sydney Film Journal (Box 14)
    - Take One (Box 14)
    - Téléciné (Box 14)
    - Unifrance Film (Box 14)
    - Video Review (Box 14)
    - Visages du Cinéma (Box 14)
    - WBAI Portfolio (Box 14)
- Series IV: Photographs, undated
  This series is comprised mostly of film stills. Films with a significant number of stills are grouped together and arranged alphabetically by title, and the film titles are listed in the finding aid. For other films with a less significant number of stills, the titles were previously handwritten on the back, though there are some stills that could not be identified. This series also contains a few headshots and portraits of directors, including Ingmar Bergman and John Ford. The series also features a small section of personal photographs, many of them portraits of Sarris’ wife, Molly Haskell.
  - Personal, headshots/portraits (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Film stills (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - 7 Women (1966) (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - A Lesson in Love (1954) (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Age of Illusions, The (1964) (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Agent 008¾ (1964) (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - An American Werewolf in London (1981) (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Arthur (1981) (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Back Roads (1981) (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Bible, The (1966) (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Blowup (1966) (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - The Boys in the Band (1970) (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Champagne Murders (1967) (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Continental Divide (1981) (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Doctor Zhivago (1965) (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Doctor Zhivago (1965) (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Fear No Evil (1981) (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Fox and the Hound, The (1981) (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Galaxina (1980) (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Halloween II (1981) (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Honky Tonk Freeway (1981) (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Hopeless Ones, The (Szegénylegények) (1966) (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Howling, The (1981) (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Marked Woman (1937) (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Middle Age Crazy (1980) (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Monika (1953) (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Naked Night, The (Sawdust and Tinsel) (1953) (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Outland (1981) (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Ox-Bow Incident (1943) (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Portrait of a Prince (1981) (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Priest of Love (1981) (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Raggedy Man (1981) (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Rules of the Game (1950) (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Sabaleros (1958) (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Smiles of a Summer Night (1955) (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - So Fine (1981) (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Something Wild in the City (1961) (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Sphinx (1981) (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Superman II (1981) (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Take This Job and Shove It (1981) (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - This Is Elvis (1981) (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Under the Rainbow (1981) (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Valley, The (1972) (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - What Did You Do in the War, DaddyÀ (1966) (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Welcome to Hard Times (1967) (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Wolfen (1981) (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - General (Box 15, Folder 13-15)
    - Unidentified (Box 15, Folder 16-17)
- Series V: Recordings, 1965-1969, undated
  This series is comprised mostly of recordings on magnetic tape of Sarris’s radio program “Films in Focus.” Though a few dates could not be determined, the majority is dated and is arranged chronologically. There is also footage of the 1980 Critics Choice Awards on two VHS tapes.
  - Films in Focus radio program, 1965-1969 (Box 16-18)
  - General recordings (Box 18)
- Series VI: Family papers, 1953-1970, undated
  This series is comprised of papers originally belonging to Sarris’s mother, Themis Sarris, and brother, George Sarris. Themis Sarris’s papers include mostly notebooks, while George Sarris’s papers include correspondence, and general materials related to his service in the military.
  - Papers of Themis Sarris (Box 19, Folder 1-2)
  - Papers of George Sarris (Box 19, Folder 3-8)
- Series VII: Personal files, 1945-1980, undated
  This series is comprised mostly of material originating from Sarris’s earlier life, and includes school records and assignments, report cards, various awards and certificates, and military records. The series also includes personal notes in small spiral notebooks. Though the series relates mostly to his personal life and pre-career, there is also a small section of publishing contracts and a framed award from the Morris Morgenstern Foundation that is housed in an oversized box.
  - School and military-related material (Box 19, Folder 9-12)
  - Notes and ephemera (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Reports (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Contracts (Box 19, Folder 15-17)
  - Morris Morgenstern Foundation Award (Box 20)